Finding Aid for Victoria Joan Moessner papers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Victoria Joan Moessner papers
1860-2011
1950-2011
Moessner, Victoria Joan.
2014007 Aa 2
Papers of Victoria Moessner,former professor of German at the University of Alaska-Fairbanks and daughter of Hans Emanuel Hansen. The Victoria Moessner papers consist largely of correspondence between Moessner and her friends, colleagues, and family. There is also information about Moessner's family history. The collection also includes papers of her father, Hans Emanuel Hansen. There are a series of family photographs in the collection dating from the mid-19th century to the 1980s.
6 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donated by Victoria Moessner (Donor No. 6787 ) in July, 2011.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Victoria Joan Moessner was born in 1937 in Ann Arbor, Michigan. She received her Bachelor's degree from Indiana University in 1959 and then went to Heidelberg to work for the University of Maryland. In 1960 she married Karlheinz Moessner and they had two daughters. Moessner returned to the United States and received her Master's (1963) and Ph.D. (1971) from the University of Michigan. From 1967 to 1973, she worked for Indiana University-Fort Wayne. In 1981 Moesnner moved to Alaska to teach German at the University of Alaska-Fairbanks. She remained there until 2007. During her time there she became well known for her translation work and publications. In the 1990s she was instrumental in keeping the German program from being cut from the curriculum.
Moessner is the daughter of Hans Emanuel Hansen. Hansen was born in Copenhagen in 1880 and immigrated to the United States in 1904. He returned to Denmark and then came back to the United States permanently in 1908. After living in various locations, Hansen settled in Ann Arbor and became a prominent member of the community.
The collection contains five series: Correspondence, Personal and Professional Papers, Family Papers, Hans Hansen Papers, and Photographs.
Subjects:
Hansen, Hans.; Danish Americans--Michigan.; Moessner, Victoria Joan.; Moessner family--Genealogy.; University of Alaska Fairbanks.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series (4 linear feet) contains correspondence between Moessner and her family, friends, and colleagues. Some of the letters have photographs attached to them. Many of the letters are in German and English. Other languages include Danish and Polish. Correspondence that consists of only one letter can be found in the unidentified folder. The unidentified folder also contains letters from writers with ineligible signatures.
  - Abrams, Peyton, 1996-2004 (Box 1)
  - Annist, Sinje, 2000s (Box 1)
  - Bardelle, Gisela, 1990s-2000s; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Stuart Becker, Stuart, 1999 (Box 1)
  - Bergdoll, Abs. Fam. K., 1960s (Box 1)
  - Berman, Gerald, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Bilicic, Wilma, 2000s (Box 1)
  - Bernd Blauert-Segna, Bernd, 1980s-2000s; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Bögli, 1990s-2000s; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Bolles, Jon, 1980s-1990s; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Borzecka, Anna, 1970s-1980s; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Böziger, Erika-Elisabeth, 2000s (Box 1)
  - Burgraf, Indrek, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Burton, Martha1970s-2000s, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Camfron, Sheila, 1970s-1980s; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Campagner, Elisabeth, 1985; 1997; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Campana, Dr. Phillip, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Carter, Mary, 1980s-1990s; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Church, Ginny, 1980s-2000s; 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Clausen, Jeanette, 1970s-2000s; 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Court, Robert, 1970s-1990s; 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Dammgaard-Iversen, Jørgen, 1980s-2000s; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Davids, Patrick, undated (Box 1)
  - Doege, Ursula, undated (Box 1)
  - Eckert, Gabriele, 1980s-2000s; 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Eifler, Ulrich, 1977-1978 (Box 1)
  - Fratti, Mario, 1960s-1970s; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Groth, Alice, 1980s-2000s; 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Hanmann, Charlotte, 1990s (Box 2)
  - Hansen, Elwood, 2000s (Box 2)
  - Hansen, Erling, 1990s-2000s; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Hamilton, Terrie, 1990s-2000s; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Hegener, Joanne, 2000s (Box 2)
  - Hennecke, L., 2000s (Box 2)
  - Hesselbo, Ingrid, 1960s-2000s; 16 folders (Box 2)
  - Hesselbo, Torben, 1986-1987 (Box 2)
  - Hinz, Michael and Sabine, 1980s-2000s; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Hoeffken, Christoph, 2004 (Box 2)
  - Holzmann, Bernd, 1980s (Box 2)
  - Homer, Donna, 1960s-2000s; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Jörger, Gisela, 1990s (Box 2)
  - Kangor, Inge, 1990s (Box 2)
  - Kannik, Helje, 2000s (Box 2)
  - Khan, Titimaeo, Colin, and Shammie, 1950s (Box 2)
  - Kirsch, Barbara, 1980s-2000s; 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Kelly, Andrew, 1980-1981 (Box 2)
  - Kranich, Brigitte, 1980s-1990s; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Kufo, Nema, 2000s (Box 3)
  - Kuhn, Annemarie, 1990s; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - La, Huong and Lan, 1980s-2000s; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Laabs, Joorhen, undated (Box 3)
  - Lang, G., 1960s (Box 3)
  - Lenhart, Sissi, 1990s-2000s; 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Lesquereux, Jacques, 1980s-1990s; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Liebchen, Ingeborg, 1998 (Box 3)
  - Loboda, Bogumila, 1970s-1990s; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Magal/Mlinarski, Ethel, 1980s-2000s; 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Matsuno, Mike, 2000s (Box 3)
  - Moessner Family, 1960s-1990s; 8 folders (Box 3)
  - Moessner, Petra, 1960s-2000s; 8 folders (Box 3)
  - Moessner, Susan and Petra, 1970s; 2000s; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Naske, Claus M., 1980s-2000s; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Nelson, Taliaferro (Tolli), 2002 (Box 3)
  - Nundel, 1980s-1990s; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Petri, Marianne, 2006 (Box 3)
  - Petzold Family, 1980s; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Pierce, Richard "Dick" A., 1980s; 6 folders (Box 3)
  - Ranee, Iahunlang, 2010 (Box 3)
  - Rappard, Renate, 1990s; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Riege, Jürgen, 1980s (Box 4)
  - Rosenthal, Dr. Erwin, 1980s-2000s; 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Ruhlig, Erwin and Karen, 2000s (Box 4)
  - Sands, Don, 1980s (Box 4)
  - Sarah, 2010 (Box 4)
  - Schenk, Ernest, 2000s; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Schenk, Rigmor, 1960s; 11 folders (Box 4)
  - Schmitt, Astrid, 1980s (Box 4)
  - Schramm, Sybille and Johannes, 2006 (Box 4)
  - Selçuk, Dr., 2000s (Box 4)
  - Smith, Mabel, 1985-2000 (Box 4)
  - Sprang, Andreas, 1980s-1990s; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Steiner, Carl, 1990s-2000s; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Streitberger, Barbara, 2000s (Box 4)
  - Szyszkowitz, Dr. Gerald, 1990s-2000s; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Tunpek-Kjellmark, Katharina, 1980s (Box 4)
  - Varnek, Jens, 1979 (Box 4)
  - Varnek, Lisbeth, 1980s (Box 4)
  - Vosmeer, Peter, 1980s-1990s; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Vogt, Ingeborg, 1980s-1990s; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Wadlow, Joan K., 1992 (Box 4)
  - Walter, Sharon, 1970s-2000s; 5 folders (Box 4)
  - Westphal, Eva, 1980s-1990s; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Wilder, Annegret, 1990s-2000s; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Wood, James, 1960s (Box 4)
  - Zauner, Friedrich, 1991-1992 (Box 4)
  - Unidentified, 1964-2008 (Box 4)
- Personal and Professional Papers
  Personal and Professional Papers series (0.5 linear feet) contains Moessner's diaries from 1985-1991. There are several folders with materials relating to Moessner's position at the University of Alaska Fairbanks. These papers detail her tenure and her fight to keep the German program from being cut. Her personal papers contain a copy of her daughter Susan's birth certificate, Moessner's marriage certificate, and early school papers. There is also an essay describing the forest of Paragon Farms.
  - Diaries, 1985; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Diary, 1986 (Box 5)
  - Diary, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Diary, 1991 (Box 5)
  - Diaries, undated; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Foreign Service, 1979-1980 (Box 5)
  - Personal (Box 5)
  - University of Alaska-Fairbanks, 1983-2007; 7 folders (Box 5)
- Family Papers
  Family Papers series (0.25 linear feet) includes correspondence and papers of Moessner's family. This series excludes Hans Hansen's papers. The correspondence ranges from 1911 to the 1970s. The unidentified folder contains letters between unknown people. The series also contains genealogical research that Moessner conducted, including correspondence between Moessner and archivists and secondary/primary sources that she found. The secondary sources are especially useful for learning more information about Martha Hansen, Hans Hansen's first wife. In 1916, Martha was admitted to the psychiatric ward of Eloise Hospital near Detroit and remained there until she returned to Denmark in 1917. The secondary source folder contains information about Martha's time at a psychiatric hospital in Denmark. There is also a narrative and family tree that describes Moessner's family history. Of particular interest to genealogists is a translated speech by Asmund Gleerup and Ole Kirk, who were Moessner's ancestors in Denmark.
  - Asmund Gleerup and Ole Kirk translated speech (Box 5)
  - Correspondence
    - Fred, August, 1907 (Box 5)
    - Ane Kirstine Hansen, undated (Box 5)
    - Ernest Schenk, 1908; 1912 (Box 5)
    - Rigmor Schenk and Elisabeth Jensen, 1920s-1960s; 6 folders (Box 5)
    - Unidentified, 1911-1970 (Box 5)
  - Helge Hansen diary (Box 5)
  - Petra Moessner papers (Box 5)
  - Research
    - Copies of photographs (Box 5)
    - Correspondence
      - Victoria Moessner and Henning Bender, 2004-2005 (Box 5)
      - Victoria Moessner and Johannes Merklein, 1980s-1990s (Box 5)
    - Family history narrative/tree (Box 5)
    - Secondary source research (Box 5)
- Hans Hansen Papers
  The Hans Hansen Papers series (0.5 linear feet) contains correspondence between Hans Hansen and his family and friends. The unidentified folders are of correspondence between Hansen and his business associates and unidentified people. The unidentified folder also contains letters between Hansen and his wife, Martha's, doctors at Eloise Hospital near Detroit. There is also a folder of letters written by various family members that have been translated to English. The series contains correspondence belonging to his first wife, Martha Hansen (Jensen), and his second wife, Victoria Hansen (Plants) to their family and friends. There are ten folders of postcards that Hansen wrote during his travels around Europe. The series also includes property information. This consists of a court case about his wife's family property in West Virginia, Victoria Hansen's will, and a folder of information about the 42 North Project (a project that involved Hansen's property). The miscellaneous folder contains Hansen's membership cards and his statement on religion.
  - Correspondence
    - Hansen family, 1940s-1960s; 4 folders (Box 5)
    - Hansen, Helge, 1920s-1950s (Box 5)
    - Hansen, Martha, 1907-1916 (Box 5)
    - Hansen, Martha, letters to family, 1902-1911 (Box 5)
    - Hansen (Plants), Victoria, 1916 (Box 5)
    - Hansen (Plants), Victoria, letters to family, 1914-1961 (Box 5)
    - Moessner (Hansen), Victoria, 1950s-1970s; 6 folders (Box 6)
    - Schenk, Rigmor, 1957-1958 (Box 6)
    - Translated letters, 1901-1960 (Box 6)
    - Unidentified, 1910s-1940s; 4 folders (Box 6)
  - Postcards
    - 1900s-1950s, 10 folders (Box 6)
  - Property
    - Calvin Paul Edwards vs. unknown heirs court case (Box 6)
    - 42 North Project (Box 6)
    - Property transfer information (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series (0.75 linear feet) contains 20 folders of photographs ranging from the 1860s to the 1980s. The bulk of the photographs are of Moessner's family.
  - 1860s-1980s, 20 folders (Box 6)
Related Collection
The Bentley Historical Library holds a related collection: The Hans Hansen papers, 1900-1958 (call number: 85182 Aa 1), papers of Moessner's father.